<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Second letter to a member of Parliament touching the growth and increase of popery in England.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58978</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2285A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R27006</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09606180</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09606180</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43808</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58978)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43808)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1339:41)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Second letter to a member of Parliament touching the growth and increase of popery in England.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Barbazon Aylmer,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholics --  England.</term>
               <term>Anti-Catholicism --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:43808:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43808:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Second LETTER to a <hi>Member of Parliament,</hi> touching the Growth and Increaſe of Popery in <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Firſt Letter to a worthy Member of your Houſe this Seſſion, touching the Growth and Increaſe of Popery in this Kingdom, having found a deſervedly kind Acceptance with all Lover<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Religion, Laws and Liberties of their Native Country, I could not but caſt in my Mite (to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Preſervation of what ſo nearly concerns us all) both as a Supplement to the Forme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Letter, and alſo as a Confirmation of it, not doubting but you will take my Well-meaning in this Addreſs, in good Part, who have already given ſuch early Proofs of a Zeal, as well as a Knowledge beyond your years.</p>
            <p>'Tis no ſmall ſatisfaction to every Honeſt Engliſh Man, and True Proteſtant, to ſee the Nation begin to awaken from that dead Sleep, in which it has, for ſome years paſt, laid [I mean as to the Ground that Popery has gotten ſince the happy Revolution in the ever Memorable Year 88.] till within a few day<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> one of another, the Two Proclamations that lately came forth, and the Reſolves of your Honourable Houſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (in the Votes of <hi>Febr.</hi> 21. laſt) do ſeem to put it beyond all doubt, that the Court, and the Parliament o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>England,</hi> do now begin in good earneſt, to Reſolve, before 'tis too late, to prevent the further Miſchief that threaten Us from that Quarter.</p>
            <p>The Petition of the Clergy of the County Palatine of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> lately laid before your Honourable Houſe, ſhews you (no doubt) the great Reaſon there is to Complain of the Inſolence of the Popiſh Emiſſaries that ſwarm in every Corner of the Land, and give out, That they have now greater Hopes, than for many years paſt, to Extirpate the Northern <hi>Hereſie,</hi> and to Eſtabliſh their Idolatrous <hi>Worſhi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in theſe Kingdoms. The Truth of which, thoſe that live near, or have any Converſation with, our pretended Engliſh Catholicks, in any Part of the Kingdom, can Teſtifie; and queſtionleſs you would hear more of this Matter from all Quarters, were there but a ſufficient Security, and a fitting Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement given to ſuch, whom, as things ſtand, either Fear or Intereſt diſcourages from the Diſcharge of their Duty to their Country, in this regard.</p>
            <p>You know well Sir, the Romaniſts (who know their own Strength and Numbers but too well) are none of the beſt Neighbours: Their very Mercies are therefore Cruel, becauſe their Malice and Reſentment know no Bounds. They are bigotted by a blind Zeal, and neither can nor will forget or forgive any ſuch as have either the Courage or the Honeſty to Oppoſe them in their pernicious Ways; ſo that 'tis left with the Wiſdom of the Nation, <q>Whether the Firſt Step to Curb the Inſolence of the Popiſh Party, be not to make ſome <hi>Effectual</hi> Proviſion for, the Security and Indemnity of ſuch Perſons of known and approved Honeſty, Integrity, and good Reputation, as ſhall adventure (for as things now ſtand, 'tis an Adventure with a witneſs) to Inform your Honourable Houſe of the Practices of the Popiſh Faction in this Kingdom.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And if ſuch Effectual Proviſion may not be made in this Juncture of Affairs, we muſt hereafter even thank our ſelves, if we are led blind-fold into <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Slavery,</hi> from which 'tis true, we were not many year<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſince deliver'd almoſt miraculouſly, tho' now, at this day, ſuch our Deliverance is almoſt forgotten; partly by our own baſe Ingratitude, and partly by the Management of our ſubtle Adverſaries, whoſe politick Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifice it is to turn all Events (whether for, or againſt them) upon Us: So that, the Emiſſaries of the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> are confeſſedly Retainers to St. <hi>Peter</hi> in this, (it in nothing elſe) that, in the worſt ſenſe they are expert <hi>Fiſhers of Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To demonſtrate this, I need carry you Sir, no further abroad than our own Country, nor further back than what is yet freſh in our Memories; I mean the Plot diſcovered in 78. 'Tis true, <hi>Coleman,</hi> ſome few Prieſts, and one Lord, ſuffer'd their deſerved Puniſhment, but for all that, <hi>They</hi> ſoon order'd the Matter ſo, as to turn the <hi>Plot</hi> upon the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and quickly ſo improved, as to get ground by it, as appear'd by their carrying their Grand Point; [I mean the Succeſſion] for which this Nation has ſince been plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully drain'd, both of her Blood and Treaſure too. And yet, conſidering who Govern'd all at Court then, 'tis no wonder that they weather'd that Storm ſo ſoon as they did. But 'tis ſurprizing to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, how fatal a Blunder they made in the following Reign, when they had the Game entirely in their own hands. There was a Time, when all, but their own <hi>Party,</hi> attributed their Miſcarriage to the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate hand of God. But the greateſt Riddle is behind, That after ſo conſpicuous a Turn of <hi>Providence,</hi> as ſcarce any Age or Hiſtory can parallel, when every body thought that Popery had been laid in its win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding-ſheet, and paſt all hopes of Recovery on this ſide of the Water; and that under ſo Excellent a Prince as our preſent Gracious King <hi>William,</hi> who is both in his Intereſts and Affections too, the moſt averſe to Romiſh Superſtition and Idolatry; and who in his Nature, abominates Popiſh Tyranny and Cruelty: I ſay, that under ſuch a Prince, and ſuch a Government as Ours is, the Papiſts ſhould get ground among Us, and pervert multitudes of people of all Ranks and Degrees, ſeems incredible, did it not too evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently appear in fact to be true. It looks as if that Infatuation, which under the Laſt Reign attended them, was in This fallen upon Us.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, during the Continuance of the late War with <hi>France,</hi> the Romaniſts, generally ſpeaking, (for ſome Deſperado's there were who puſh'd at all, having nothing but a worthleſs Life to loſe) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> themſelves more upon the reſerve than they have done ſince the Concluſion of the General Peace. The only Diſcouragement they have hitherto lain under, (and in which they are not alone) is the Double Tax; which, as their Eſtates have been very much undervalued by their Creatures, Tools, or Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, has been reduced to near the Half Value, and conſequently. They have paid no more than their Neighbours (if ſo much, in ſome places eſpecially) where their Eſtates at Rack-Rent have been Aſſeſſed in the Tenants Name, if a <hi>Proteſtant.</hi> Nay, tho' the <hi>Papiſts</hi> occaſioned the War, and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of the Treaſure, which year by year the War required:Yet ſo merciful was the Government to them all along, as to leave it to their own Choice, whether they would pay double Taxes or not,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:43808:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
when ſome people thought they had not been too hardly dealt withal, if ſo be their Eſtates had been Confiſcate towards the Charge of the War whilſt it continued, and till the Nation was out of Debt, even in the Time of <hi>Peace</hi> too.</p>
            <p>If this ſeems to ſound a little too harſh, (as why ſhou'd it? ſeeing, as I ſaid, they occaſioned the War) what ſhould hinder, if there were due Encouragement, and Security for ſuch as ſhall diſcover them, but all the Jeſuites, and other Seminaries Lands in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> bought up with their Moneys, only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n Truſt, and in the Names of the pretended Catholicks, ſhould be ſeized, and ſold for the Uſe of the <hi>Publick?</hi> Conſidering that theſe Vermin do plant themſelves here among us, to no other end, but to ruine and deſtroy us. If, in our own Defence, we may not diſable ſuch Adverſaries, as (if let alone) will ſoon grow upon us, and trample us under their feet, and ſhew us no more Mercy than a <hi>Turk</hi> ſhew'd a <hi>Saracen,</hi> then are we in a piteous Caſe. They deal not ſo tenderly by their old Refugees, nor by their ſuſpected New Converts abroad, as we deal by them; but if the ſame Meaſure was given them nearer home, that they give the poor <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in other Countries, they were ſerved but in their kind, tho' our Holy Religion will not ſuffer us ſo far to Unman our ſelves.</p>
            <p>They were not ſo bold and aſſuming (as I hinted even now) before the late Peace was concluded, but they have been much more ſo ſince; as they concluded ('tis probable) that the former Alliance was in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect broken, upon Concluſion of a General Peace: And the <hi>E.</hi> and <hi>K.</hi> of <hi>Sp.</hi> might probably be brought over, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And beſides, ſince the Peace, the Ports have been more open on both ſides of the Channel, than in the time of War; ſo that they have chuſed, and rechuſed (almoſt at pleaſure) and by that means have filled our Lands with ſuch Locuſts and Caterpillars as you may every Day hear Complaints of (and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry deſervedly too) from every Quarter.</p>
            <p>Above an Year and half ſince their pretended Bp. <hi>Gifford</hi> viſited the Weſtern Parts of <hi>England,</hi> and confirmed Multitudes, and that ſo openly too, that almoſt every body in the Neighbourhood where he came, knew to what intent he was come, and what he did at his ſeveral Stages, how he was regaled like a Prince by the Grandees of his Party, and even adored by the common People.</p>
            <p>Since which their Ignorant Admirers are poſſeſſed with a Conceit, that at the begining of the following Age, 1700. they ſhall ſee Popery ſettled here, and in other Countries, and the Proteſtant Religion every where utterly rooted out. Now Sir, tho' this ſeems to be only a fooliſh Surmize of theirs, and not much to be regarded by us; yet, being once entertained with a Credulity that's peculiar to That Party (as the Vulgar are eaſily brought to believe that it will be, which they would have be) and being improved by their crafty Prieſts, who as they are Maſters of the Conſciences and Purſes too of their deluded Partizans; ſo they never let their Spirits ſink (if they can by any means keep them up) under any preſſure, they by experience find will work Wonders, and have the like effect among their People, that the Doctrine of Fate hath among the Turks; that is, 'twill make the One as freely run their Heads againſt a Wall, as the Other go boldly up to, and charge, even at, the mouth of a fiered Canon.</p>
            <p>And tho' their Creatures and Proſelytes are obliged on an implicit Belief, and without Examination, to take down in the Lump whatever their Guides infuſe into them, and to believe it (tho' Contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the Reaſon of all Mankind beſides) as firmly as if it were Goſpel: Yet 'tis not to be doubted but they (I mean their blind Guides) do deſignedly encourage their credulous People with certain hopes of ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their accurſed Enterprizes upon this Church and Nation, by filling their Heads with ſome plauſible ground upon which ſuch hopes and expectations are built: And ſuch probably are the reſtleſs Endeavours of the Jeſuits abroad, to break the Old Confederacy or Alliance, and to ſet on Foot and Confirm a New One; by which two ſticks (not to ſay more) may be made One, and therewith they imagin they ſhall one Day quit their old Scores with us, and Cudgel us obſtinate Hereticks into better manners.</p>
            <p>Another ground they build much upon (as well they may) is our unhappy Diviſions, and unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Heats and Animoſities at home, within our ſelves; and the no good Terms the Proteſtant Princes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad are at, one with another; for if the Emiſſaries of that Church, who are Maſters of that curſed Matchiavilian Policy, can but once divide a People within themſelves, they never deſpair of compaſſing their Ends upon them, at ſome time or other.</p>
            <p>Beſides the over-eaſie Careleſsneſs and Security of many well-meaning People among us, who have been too ſanguine, and thought that all danger of the return of Popery and Tyranny was over; when <hi>K. J.</hi> and the pretended <hi>Pr.</hi> and Fa. <hi>Peters</hi> were once ſcamper'd; have been wonderfully improved to our hurt by the Romiſh Party, for more than 10 Years together laſt paſt.</p>
            <p>To which if we add the unparallell'd Tenderneſs and Compaſſion of the Government hitherto, and of many of the inferior Magiſtracy (in all parts of the Kingdom) towards them [the Papiſts] and that too, at a time when the Proteſtants Intereſt has ſenſibly been ſinking every where abroad, and its Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors perſecuted even to Death, the Gallies, Bonds and Impriſonments; I ſay, where ſo little Oppoſition has for ſo many Years (thro' a miſtaken pitty, or ſomething worſe) been made, to put a ſtop to its In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and Growth, That ſo many of our People have been perverted by their indefatigable Emiſſaries, is ſo far from being a wonder, that it may rather ſeem very ſtrange to one who ſhall ſeriouſly reflect on theſe Things, that they have not before now made themſelves Maſters of both our Place and Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on too.</p>
            <p>But (to ſpeak to the Merits of the Cauſe) if the real Advantages the Romaniſt have on their ſide, be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amin'd and lookt into, it muſt needs be ſaid that the Wonder will ſtill increaſe, how we have hitherto eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped that utter Deſtruction, which for the Courſe of ſo many Years, they, under ſo many various Diſguiſes, and by manifold Ways and Means, have all along ſince the Reformation, been attempting to accompliſh and bring about.</p>
            <p>I ſhall Sir, with your patience, but juſt mention ſome of the moſt obvious Methods they have taken, and the unhappy Succeſs (as to us) that thoſe Methods have met with, as to the promoting of their grand Deſign upon us. All which I humbly ſubmit to the grave Judgment, and Conſideration of our Repreſentatives in Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, that they in their great Wiſdom may take ſuch ſpeedy and effectual Courſe to put a ſtop to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of the Evils complain'd of, as they ſhall think fit.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:43808:2"/>
            <p>It cannot then be deny'd but the Papiſts have a vaſt Advantage over us, in reſpect of their Unity within themſelves; for by the Authority their Prieſts uſurp over their Conſciences, they are all as one Man in their common Cauſe, which is the pulling us down, and ſetting themſelves up. To accompliſh which, their Oaths of Secrecy bound upon them by Sacraments too, do make it almoſt impoſſible for Man to penetrate into their hidden Works of Darkneſs; their Doctrines of Merit, and of blind Obedience to their Superiors with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſerve, do ſtand them in great ſtead too: And ſo does the vaſt Number of their ſeveral Orders in that Church; and the Multitude of deſigning Men in every one of thoſe Orders, who ſtick at no Difficulties, and leave nothing unattempted to effect our utter Extermination. In order to which they turn themſelves into all manner of Diſguiſes, ſtrike in with all ſorts of Factious, or ill diſpoſed Perſons, create Diviſions and Miſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings among Proteſtants, and blow them up into a Flame, and then make their Advantages upon both the contending Parties. The Poet's Proteus himſelf could never appear in greater variety of Shapes, than the Romiſh Prieſts do amongſt us, aſſume at this Day. They can act the parts of Non Jurors in the Church; of Officers in the Camp; of Merchants on the Exchange; and ſo down from the fine Beaux to the meaneſt Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanicks. And by this means do they herd, and mingle, with all ſorts of People, and make themſelves Maſters of their Tempers, Humors and Inclinations, and then they tamper with, and work upon, them accordingly.</p>
            <p>And this they are the better enabled to do, becauſe moſt of their Orders have not only Lands of their own (as I intimated before) but alſo mighty Summs of Money to each Order belonging, ſo that by Vertue of the Banks they have in moſt Countries in <hi>Europe;</hi> the Jews themſelves have not a better Credit for Remittances to any parts of the World, than they. By which means they do not only buy up as many neceſſitous People as come in their way, if they find them fit for their purpoſe; but are enabled alſo to buy off all ſuch Puniſhments too, as, upon diſcovery, their Crimes expoſe them to, (if they can meet with any Perſons of ſo proſtitute a Conſcience, as to expoſe their very Souls, and much more than their Country, to Sale for Money) and thus do they ſometimes ſtrike off old Scores, and run up new ones forthwith, and that with Impunity for the moſt part.</p>
            <p>But beſides theſe, they of the Romiſh Perſwaſion are ſaid to have not a few of their Party, who, as <hi>Fitton</hi> and <hi>Allybone</hi> heretofore did, ſtudy the Common Law in our Inns of Court, the better to enable them to defend their own Party, and to offend us too, whoſe Security, under God, lies in thoſe very Laws which thoſe Romaniſts, who are ſuffered to intrude into thoſe Societies, do only ſtudy to elude, or overthrow. And beſides, thoſe who do thus by Connivance: find Admiſſion into our Inns of Court, (not very much for the Credit of thoſe otherwiſe very Honourable Societies) there to acquaint them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the Theory of the Law; they have many others both in City and Country too, who are bred up to the <hi>Chicanerie,</hi> or wrangling part, or the Practice of the Common Law, and became Solicitors, Petty-Foggers and Make-bates, who ſet honeſt People together by the Ears, that they may pick their Pockets. This is not only a Diſcouragement to Proteſtants, who are duly qualify'd for that Calling, and whoſe Bread thoſe Popiſh Solicitors do eat out of their Heads: But that Party makes a vaſt Advantage, (not to ſay many) by the Practice of ſuch Solicitors, who by conveyancing, and letting out peoples Money, by making their laſt Wills, and ſoliciting in all ſorts of Buſineſs, do well know the Strength or Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of all the Country round about them, and are by thoſe Means acquainted with the Humours, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers and Diſpoſitions of the ſeveral Parties, with, or for whom they are concerned. And the Conſequence is, that ſuch little Buſie-Fellows from time to time, give in an Account unto their Superiors of their Knowledge and daily Obſervations by them made. By which Means, the Heads of that Party in <hi>England,</hi> do very probably know better than our ſelves, our Strength and Weakneſs, and who are for, who againſt them too. And no Body can teach them, how to make ſuch Information turn them to very good Account. And 'tis too well known to be denyed, that ſome of thoſe ſly Popiſh Factors have ſo cajoled thoſe poor deluded people (tho' Proteſtants) among whom they live, as ſcarce to have paid, in Eleven Years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo much as a ſingle Poll-Tax of Twelve pence. But that other ſome of the ſame Stamp and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, ſhould for 5 Years together, continue their practice without ſatisfying the World, that they have ever taken the Oath of Fealty, as required, after the Aſſaſſination plot, by an Act of Parliament, is ſuch a bare-faced and open Defiance to the Laws of the Land, and to the Legiſlative too, by whom they are E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacted, as is perhaps without all preſident. However, 'tis to be hoped now that the Honourable Houſe of Commons is upon retrenching the Number of Attorneys and Solicitors, that they will in their Great Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom begin with ſuch as I have been ſpeaking of, whoſe Inſolence is intollerable, and whoſe Impudence is, any other way, incureable.</p>
            <p>There's another Advantage the Papiſts make by the pretended Merit of good Works, or a feigned Shew of Charity to Proteſtants: For though they mortally hate all thoſe (not of their own way) upon whom they beſtow their treacherous Mock-Charities, as they curſe us at the leaſt once in the Year in their ſolemn Devotions, by Bell, Book and Candle: Yet, they throw out a fine guilded Bait under a deadly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidious Hook, to catch the ignorant, unſteady common people, who judge only by the out-ſide of things. Thus the Schooling of ſome poor Proteſtants Children is paid in ſome places, even by Jeſuits themſelves, upon Condition that ſuch Children ſhall read only in ſuch Books, (of which you may be ſure the Bible is not one) as thoſe their Benefactors ſhall at free coſt furniſh them withal. In other places up and down, they have Midwives, and Women-Doctreſſes, who dabble in Phyſick and Chyrurgery, who, under pretence of much Tenderneſs to thoſe Bodies, which they could, were it in their power, conſume in a <hi>Smith-field</hi> Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire, do lay in wait for, and ſometimes catch in their Snare, an ignorant unſtable <hi>Soul:</hi> Which having perverted, they make twofold more a Child of <hi>Hell</hi> than themſelves. Under this Head, (had I not been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by the worthy Author of the firſt Letter) I ſhould have expoſed their bold practices in haunting, and tampering with, ſuch perſons as are ſick or declining (eſpecially if their by-paſt Lives have been ſuch, as to need a Feather bed to carry them to Heaven upon) and their ranſacking of Priſons, and their gleaning or picking up of Proſelytes at the very Gallows; by all which we may plainly perceive, that they ſtick not to compaſs Sea and Land, ſo they may obtain their Ends upon us.</p>
            <p>I have but one Thing more Sir, to trouble you at this time withal. I am well ſatisfied of your Sted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtneſs in the eſtabliſhed Religion, and of the due reſpect you always ſhew to ſuch of our Clergy as are an
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43808:3"/>
Ornament to their Station, by the Conſtancy of their Faith, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>larity of their Lives, the diligent Diſcharge of their Functions, and their Loyalty to the preſent King, our Gracious Sovereign Lord <hi>William</hi> the Third, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now Sir, theſe are the Men that of all others are the Objects of the Papiſts mortal Hatred; and if it be the Misfortune of any honeſt Clergy-man of ſuch a Character, to have a popiſh Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron; he is ſure, to live as uneaſie in his Poſt, as They and their Agents can (or durſt attempt to) make him. I make no doubt therefore, but you will permit me to intercede for all ſuch of the Clergy as ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer upon the aforeſaid Account; nor can I in the leaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> diſtruſt Their having as many Advocates, as Friend, in your Honourable Houſe. 'Tis the general Concern of the eſtabliſht Church, that the Right of Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage of Eccleſiaſtical Benefices ſhould be placed in other Hands, than Theirs, whoſe only purpoſe it is to root out and to deſtroy the Church of <hi>England;</hi> Their Benefices are either Sold, or beſtowed ſo, as to be made rather a Snare, than a free Gift to the Procurer. There's no great harm in the Firſt, (provided the Governours of the Church could be aſſured well of this, that the wealthieſt Clerks would always make the beſt Parſons, Vicars, or Curates) ſo in this caſe, if the Danger of Simony be avoided, a Man may (if he thinks fit) part with his Money to thoſe Patrons, or their Agitators, and yet preſerve his Liberty. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, the other way, a Man is ſhuckled of courſe; for either through want of Learning or Parts, Morality of Honeſty (as the choice is commonly made) the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> such Tools as cannot, or elſe ſuch, as thro' Fear or Fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs of Spirit, or ſome other mean and ſordid conſideration, will not ſtand their Ground, and defend their Flocks, when they ſee the Wolf a coming to worry and to devour them. To remedy which Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies, two Acts of Parliament have been made (the latter in or about the Year 90) to inveſt the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings of all Recuſants in Both the Univerſities. For what reaſon they have not thought fit to look after Their Concern in it, they do beſt know, it concerns not me to enquire. However this Their tacit Diſclaimer has encouraged ſuch Patrons as are Recuſants to elude the Law, and to laugh at it, and the Univerſities too. Nay, ſince that Act laſt mentioned, 'tis well known, that the Market runs higher than ever in all parts of <hi>England.</hi> And yet 'tis thought the next or reverſional Preſentations of moſt of their Livings are diſpoſed of, many of them at exceſſive Rates too. But admitting they are ſo, yet what ſhould hinder, but ſome Care may be taken of Poſterity? Or why might not theſe Livings be inveſted in the K by Act of Parliament, and Commiſſioners appointed, as to ratifie ſuch Grants as are already on Foot, ſo to diſpoſe of the Reman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der or perpetual Advowſon? And conſidering the Hardships thoſe Incumbents have ſubmitted to, who have obtained ſuccedaneous Preſentations after others, or after themſelves; why might not ſuch be allow'd the Preemption or Firſt Refuſal? And next to them any other perſon qualifyed by Law, that is, being a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd Proteſtant, and having taken the Oaths, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By this means the Preferments would ſoon be placed in better Hands, and the Inconveniences before mentioned in a great Meaſure, (if not altogether) would be removed, and a conſiderable Sum advanced, either to augment the poorer Vicarages and Curacies, or for ſuch other charitable Uſes, as His Majeſty and Both Houſes of Parliament ſhall think fit to appropriate or apply it to.</p>
            <p>If it be objected, That to ſtrip Recuſants of the Right of the Patronage of their Livings, is an Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip upon them. This is ſoon Anſwer'd: Firſt, That ſuch Patronage, or Right to fill a <hi>Church</hi> when vacant, is a great Truſt, for GOD, and His <hi>Church,</hi> or <hi>People:</hi> Now where this Truſt is gotten into ſuch hands as can't but abuſe it, and proſtitute is to the moſt ſcandalous and vile purpoſes; there ſuch incureable Abuſe of a Truſt, does in many like caſes forfeit the Truſt; and if ſo, Why not in this caſe? eſpecially if the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, weight, and moment of the Abuſe be duly conſidered. <hi>Secondly,</hi> 'Tis plain, that the <hi>KING, Lords,</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> have more than once, by the Laws even now mentioned, virtually declared a Forfeiture of ſuch Truſt in the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Patrons, by transferring their Right of Preſenting to, and Inveſting them in, Both the Univerſities. And therefore, <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The ſame Supream Authority may Inveſt them other where, if it thinks fit, upon the Incureable Abuſe of this Great Truſt; ſo that their Right of Preſenting may as juſtly be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd to the King, as to the Univerſities: Neither is it enough to ſay, that in this caſe, there's an Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip upon ſome particular perſons, which is inconſiſtent with Juſtice; For, <hi>Fourthly,</hi> a private Good, muſt (in Reaſon) give way to a publick One: Now the Hardſhip does really lye upon the whole <hi>Church of England,</hi> if the particular Churches are ill-provided for: The Injury in ſuch Caſe redounds to a far greated number of private perſons (as it may happen) in one particular Cure or Pariſh, than there are popiſh Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons in the whole Kingdom. In fine, Sir, if thoſe Recuſant-Patrons do follow the Direction of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily-prieſts indiſpoſing of their Benefices (as no Body can doubt but they do.) I ſuppoſe it will be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that their Prieſts will not have ſo much Tenderneſs for Ours, as to ſcruple the drawing them into Simony; but if there's nothing of that, but only a reverſional Preſentation is bought [the Incumbent being alive and in good health,] then if (as moſt people think it does) the Money goes to the Prieſt, it is ſoon made a part of their <hi>Corban,</hi> or the Treaſure of their Church, and how far that's employed to ruine Ours, you have been told before. So that our abuſed Clergy do juſt as wiſely in this caſe, as thoſe Traders did in the late War, who furniſhed <hi>France</hi> with Lead and Salt-petre, the better to enable them to deſtroy our Armies, to annoy our Coaſts, to burn our Towns, to take our Shipping, and to ruin us in our Trade.</p>
            <p>I fear Sir, I have exceeded my bounds (tho' there's ſtill in reſerve, and behind, what would ſwell this Letter into a Volume, ſhould I deſcend to particulars) however if theſe general hints, or any one of them, ſhall, in any thing, advantage the publick, (which is the only aim of this paper:) Then I ſhall neither deſpair of obtaining Your Pardon, nor repent of running any other Hazard, but that of offending Your Self; not ſo much for my Zeal in this Cauſe, as for the meaneſt of my Performance. And yet I have no great reaſon to fear, but that if your diſcerning Judgement approves of the One, Your great Candor and Ingenuity will put a favourable Cenſure upon the other. I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt Humble and Obedient Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for <hi>Brabazon Aylmer</hi> at the <hi>Three Pigeons</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> 1700. <hi>Price</hi> 2d.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
